我们来复习一下
Let's review.
至今为止 我们知道了线性布局可以设定方向
So far we've learned that a linear layout can have an orientation that's
水平或是垂直
horizontal or vertical.
但是且让我们再想想这些布局是否充分利用了
But now let's think about whether these views are taking full advantage of
屏幕的地皮
the screen real estate.
当我说“地皮”的时候 我是说屏幕的可利用空间
When I say real estate, I mean the available space on the screen.
拿我们的Nexus6来说
For our Nexus 6 phone,
我们在一个线性布局里面有三个TextView
say we have a vertical linear layout that has three child text views inside.
其为Tom Tim 和Todd
Tom, Tim and Todd.
当我们像这样垂直地把设备握在手里时
When we hold the device in portrait mode like this in our hand,
所有的TextView就都聚集在屏幕的左上角
then all the text views are grouped in the top left corner of the screen.
这些就是所有没有用到的空白区域
There's all this blank space left unused.
相似地 如果我们把设备旋转到水平模式
Similarly, if we rotated the device to Landscape mode,
文字就会在左上角 这边则是所有剩下的空白区域
then the text is on the top left corner and there's all this blank space left.
在平板设备上更为明显
It's even more noticeable on a tablet device,
因为平板更大
where the screen is a lot bigger.
我们只使用屏幕的一小块地皮
We're only using a small amount of the screen real estate, and
剩下的就是空白
the rest of it is blank.
我们将会学习到怎么更为均衡地平铺这些View
We're going to learn about how we can more equally spread out these views
以更好地利用空余空间
across the screen to take up more of the available room.
这对其他View来说 也同样适用
This applies to other views as well.
你可以把图片占据整个屏幕空间
You can have bigger images across the screen for
以获得更好地用户体验 而非放在左上角
a better experience, instead of having them really tiny in the top left corner.
按钮同理
Same with buttons,
你可以搞一些大一点的按钮方便按上去
you could have bigger buttons so that it's easier To tap on those buttons.
为了举例方便 我们将专注于TextView
For the purposes of our example, we're going to stick with text views.
我们前往XML可视化器看看怎么布局
So let's go to the XML visualizer to figure out how we can spread out
这些View
these views.
这就是Tom Tim 和Todd 的代码
So here's the code for Tom, Tim, and Todd.
我在垂直线性布局里面有三个TextView
I have three text views within a vertical linear layout and
这就是他们在设备上的样子
this is what they look like on the device.
现在 我想让你看看怎么布局这三个TextView
Now, I want to show you how you can spread out these three text views.
Tom在这里
So that Tom is up here.
Tim在这里
Tim is here.
Todd在这里
And Todd is down here.
显然 把高度设为wrap_context没有用
Clearly, setting height for wrap_content is not doing the job.
另一个我们可以做的事情就是给高度设定一个固定的dp值
The other thing we learned is to set a fixed dp value for the height.
那么我就给高度设定为200dp
So I'm going to set the height to be, for example, 200dp.
好 这给Tom留出了很大一部分空间
Cool. So that left a lot more space for Tom.
如果我对其他的TextView也做同样的事情
If I do the same for the other TextViews,
他们就会在屏幕上均衡地分布
then they also spread out more evenly across the screen.
但是这只是对一个设备起作用
But this solution will only work for the sides of a device.
如果我有一个平板 这些View
If I have a tablet like I showed you earlier, then these views are still
还将会在左上角聚集
going to be grouped in somewhat of the top left corner.
另一个设定高度的方法是我们先前学到的match_parent
The other option for setting height is match parent which we learned earlier.
当你为Tom设定match_parent的时候
When you set match parent for the Tom TextView
它就会和整个屏幕的高度一样
it takes the height of the whole parent which is a whole screen.
这就把其他TextView推到了屏幕之外
That pushes the other text views off the screen so you can't even see them.
最好不要那么做
So let's not do that.
我们已经没有办法了 因为我们试过了wrap_content
Well now we're out of ideas because we tried wrap content for
设定固定的dp值
the height, which had a fixed DP value.
还有match_parent
And we tried match parent.
没有一个能够给出适用于所有设备的布局方案
And none of those give us the right spacing across all different devices.
我们就Google一下 查找可能的解决方案
Let's Google search for a potential solution to this problem.
我们使用线性布局的ViewGroup
We're using a linear layout view group.
我们想要均衡分布子元素
And we want to equally space out the children views.
我们搜一下
So let's search for that.
好 现在有一堆搜索结果了
Okay, so there's a bunch of search results, but
让我们点击第一个
let's click on this first one.
这是一个StackOverflow的链接
This is a link to the Stackoverflow site.
这是一个从其他Android开发者里获取答案的
It's a Q&amp;A site where you can post questions and
问答社区
get answers from other Android developers.
当我有问题的时候我总会使用它
I use it all the time when I'm stuck and I need help on a problem.
更通常的是 其他人已经问了一个
Often times other people will have already asked a question
我有的同样的问题
that I'm having.
这个问题是怎么均衡地在线性布局上
So this question here is about how to evenly distribute buttons
等宽度地放置按钮
across the width of a linear layout.
这和我们正在寻找的答案相似
This is similar to what we're looking for,
除了按钮这一点 我们是TextView
except instead of buttons we're working with text views.
还有这里是线性布局的宽度 我们要处理的是
And instead of the width of the linear layout we're trying to spread it across
在高度上均衡分布
the height of the linear layout.
我们可以通读问题
We can read through the question or we can skim it.
通常我只跳到答案
Usually I just skim for the answer.
这个解答得到了88个投票并且已被采纳
So this solution received 88 votes and has a green checkmark on it.
这个是教你设置layout_width到0dp
It talks about how you can set layout_width to 0dp and
并且把layout_weight设置为1
set the layout_weight for each of the buttons to be 1.
这就把可用的宽度均衡地划分给按钮
And that splits the available width equally across the buttons.
你可能目前还不完全理解这个答案 这没关系
You may not fully understand the answer at this point, but that's okay.
一个关键词语是我们看到了layout_weight
One key phrase that we saw is this linear layout_weight.
我们以前从未见过它 但是看起来这个是答案的关键
We haven't encountered this before, but it sounds important to the answer.
于是我们复制之并Google一下
So lets copy it and Google search for
以寻找更多的关于layout_weight的内容
more information Information about layout_weight.
于是我们搜索linear layout layout_weight
So let's search for linear layout layout_weight.
第一个结果是一篇关于linear layout的文章
The first result is an article for linear layout and
在developer.android.com上面 我们打开它
it's on the developer.android.com site, so let's click on it.
这个是一篇线性布局的文章
So this is an article about the Linear Layout.
我们已经学习了在上面有关Android方向属性的东西
We already learned the stuff at the top about the Android orientation attribute,
但是仍然有新的东西 叫做布局权重(Layout Weight)
but then there's new information about something called Layout Weight.
底下还有一个新的例子 还有一些代码
There's also an example at the bottom of the screen here with some code and
和截图
a screenshot.
我可以为你总结所有这些
I could summarize all of this for
但是我首先想给你一个机会自己尝试读这些文档
you, but first I want to give you a chance to read this document.
试着自己搞明白他们在讲什么
And try to figure it out on your own.
这和你自己去解决问题的情况很相似
This is going to be a lot more similar to how you're going to solve problems
而这往往在课堂之外
after this course is over.
你会在网上查找一些资料并且
You'll look for some information online and
试着去理解怎么应用于解决我的问题
try to figure out how that can be used to solve your problem.
好 这是一个我们在设备上已经有的布局
Okay, so this is the layout that we have now on the device.
这是我们想要达到的效果
And this is what we want to achieve.
这三个text在我们的设备上的高度均衡分布
The three texts are spread-out evenly across the height of the device.
为解决这个问题
To solve this problem,
我想让你阅读我们在下方的Linear Layout文章的链接
I want you to read the Linear Layout article that we linked below.
这完全符合你
It's perfectly normal for
不理解文章内容的境况
you to not understand everything that's in the article.
通常你只是想要对文章有一个大致的了解
Often times you just want to have some vague understanding
并希望能把其中概念用于帮助你的实际工作
of how the concepts in the article may be able to help you in your work.
然后我就会给你一些点子 帮助你在XML里面
Then I want you to provide some ideas on how we can build this desired
构建理想的XML
layout in XML.
你没必要提供所有的XML布局代码
You don't need to provide the full XML layout code
我们会在下一个视频里一起解决
because we're going to walk through that together in the next video.
但是你可以写下一两句话
But here you could write a couple sentences or
或是一些点子 告诉我们这文章里的信息怎么与我们的问题相联系
bullet points on how the information in the article could relate to our problem